so about ordination
how necessary is it to
officially ordain as a buddhist monk
in order to practice saddam hmm
it's in itself it's not
it's not necessary to
go through like the formal
um
coordination and acceptance and so on
what is necessary is the lifestyle
so
the uh the non
the life lifestyle that's free from
household is concerned let's put it that
way that's necessary for like a complete
that's necessary for like a complete
liberation from suffering
so uh
of course
there's a greater likelihood you're
gonna find the suitable or have access
to suitable environment for practice
that's free from household life concerns
if you're a monk or not
at least theoretically
you you have you have a better chance
because um
um
the ordained lifestyle generally into
like a say
the the practice tradition you know just
like a temple tradition
um
is is better than than you know crowded
and dusty
lifestyle of a householder
but that's not necessarily so
that's not necessarily so
in a sense you might
ordain you might join a community
you might join a community
and be equally busy and full of daily
concerns about you know running the
temple and duties and all sorts of stuff
that can then seem justified in doing
because oh well look this is for the
greater good of dharma or the monastery
but in reality the motivation is the
same as it is of a householder who is
just you know going being busy around
and just doing random stuff to keep
himself occupied
so that's pretty much the distinction
that a person needs to make will
if i were to ordain would that improve
my circumstances
would that provide
better grounds for keeping the vineyard
a better seclusion
more time for reflection
or would it sort of
not really meet those requirements or
sometimes you might not be able to find
something that would be
that would be
so like a black and white good or bad it
might be something in between
such as well you know
he would not he's not providing as much
seclusion as i would want he's not
providing as much as the basis but it
has potential to do so more than my
current living situation then yeah then
it's still better today
but in and of itself wearing robes or
whatever makes really makes no
difference it's just an external
statement that's it internally makes no
difference yeah
yeah
because i was thinking like
what's really
necessary is going forth as in being prepared to
is going forth as in being prepared to
leave
your the household life yeah that's yeah
i'm wondering if that necessarily sort
of
implies yeah uh wearing robes and being a
yeah uh wearing robes and being a
buddhist monk and in some cases like i'm
even thinking
if you just look purely at the lifestyle
you can see certain people as you know
house not monks
but you're just living certain kind of
lifestyles that
are quite solitary or quite
kind of remote and that's quieter less
less crowded less distracting no
definitely but i think what is pretty
much probably
the main thing here is the intention of
the person doing it
because see you you know we can you can
have argument for both sides you can say
no it's still better to be a monk
or you can say well no see if if my
household life is actually quieter more
secluded more remote it's better to be
that well again in and of itself it's
not a decisive factor what is the size
of factories your reasons behind
choosing to do whatever you choose to do
so you can have people who
might have a very good lay conditions
quiet remote
remote
not crowded plenty of time to practice
however all of their life that life is
still rooted in simply being afraid to
let go
of your environment
so you can say the environment is
externally extremely suitable for
practice of dharma internally it isn't
because it's all based on the intention
of you refusing to give up out of fear
or whatever yes
equally you can have somebody giving
everything up in like a finger snap
committing unwavering determination to
become a monk yet all it's rooted in
this quite common view
that people have which is oh as long as
i become a monk join the monastery wear
the ropes that's it practice will from
then onwards be done by the environment
all i need to do is is get there and
then i'm sort of
safe safe or something like that and
that's also not the case and that's it
entire donation there
is rooted in completely wrong reason
so the intentions behind doing it is
probably the most important to be clear
about that and then you would know
why you're not attaining
and you would know why you're staying a
lemon or you would know why you're not
staying alive and why you're learning
you wouldn't use one to kind of avoid
the other or cover responsibility for it
because what's interesting also like
you become a buddhist monk and now
there's all sorts of things
you don't do or you do
and that are sort of
automatically uh
uh
justified in your certain environment
because now you're a buddhist monk
that's something i find interesting it's
like whereas if you're
not a buddhist monk as a as a lay person
doing things like for example
practicing centrist sense restraints
spending time in seclusion not engaging
in all sorts of things
it's you really have to be sure about why
you really have to be sure about why
you're doing them or you have to work
harder in a way to
make it clear to yourself why you're
doing them instead of
i'm a monk and this is what monks do
yeah that's that's what i meant like
that can become an excuse then
uh then people the monks would then be
practicing sensory strain keeping the
rules adhering to all sorts of
observances out of a sense of duty
not out of a center that you know taking
responsibility for it
and then that means as soon as that
environment changes
your context will be compromised
um and you don't want that i mean if you
have any wisdom you realize no my
practice should be
developing me in a way that even my
circumstances change even if i end up in
a hospital or monastery gets destroyed
or i have to whatever
internally composure will not change
i will not depend on these circumstances
that are quite you know tailored and
protective of
certain sets and routines and then that
kind of allow me to sort of just you
know stop thinking about it
stop thinking about it
and uh yeah that's completely
misguided yeah
it's like the should be should be
that
it is the
choice to live a certain lifestyle that
kind of makes you a monk
rather than yeah you have a certain
lifestyle just because the difference
between like kind of formally doing it
is again it is something that you can
sort of
um that you can't really like to
yourself like if say if you're not
if you say i don't want to ordain
because you know i have a good
environment here and i have a you know
secluded property and so on and i can
live as a layman restraint and practice
fine but as i said
but as i said
more often than not they'll be losing
some sort of fear and still having a
thread of safety like well it doesn't
work out i can still do this
so from that point of view actually
formally ordaining will cut that threat
and so if but if you're honest that
would be obvious and then you would know
whether you should or not but if you
genuinely know where the practice is
generally just need a seclusion
environment to amplify it
then again you wouldn't then you would
you could stay a limit or change your
lifestyle as in layman not formally
ordained and still not live like a householder
and still not live like a householder
either
but for that already you know some
wisdom is is quite necessary some
authenticity and transparency would be
mandatory but you could probably say it's
but you could probably say it's
mandatory in all cases because if you're
not yes from the beginning yeah because
i think a monk will not necessarily make
you more yeah yeah yeah
so if i can
paraphrase it's is it about
what will make me give up
the thing that i would be holding on to
or what would be
uh putting me into
what would be putting me into the
situation that forces me to practice
more seriously yeah yeah and sometimes
like that's obviously thing if things
would be clear on that level sometimes
then it might be a bit of both and
and
in those cases you just need to kind of
um
try and think like okay okay in the long
run so
yes you know
i'm afraid to give up a household life
but at the same time i'm afraid if i
don't become a monk and stay a
householder so so what do i do here
well again don't cover up that
situation
endure it without necessarily making
your current household
environment worse
because sometimes people like oh
i want to then but if i don't then i
have to get married i was like well no
you can still live and practice the
dharma accordingly even without wearing
ropes so you you don't need to go the other
so you you don't need to go the other
way
but if it feels like it's either or
means okay well that's really the
problem it's not that you're not a monk
yet or that you're still household the
problem is that you can't
like restrain yourself and sustain that
that middle
like yes you don't need to become a monk
but that doesn't mean no but i can so
because i can't become a monk
for some reason that means i can now
engage in sensuality
uh without any kind of responsibility or
fault and that's i think i even did that talk
and that's i think i even did that talk
once like and even if
if that if dhamma is your your goal even
if you're not a monk there is no excuse
to go to sensuality it just isn't but
there is something mistaken like no i
really want to become a monk but you
know some so i can't get the visa or
something like that or my mother's sick
have to look after her some
externally valid reason that currently
prevents your money so in the meantime
oh yeah i'll find a partner and mary and
so on it's like well no that's now
completely separate set of decisions
uh that uh that you you don't need to
engage either you don't need to engage
with them either
yeah because i mean let's say
for example let's say you had the suttas
or you had access to teaching but there
were no order of monks
you'd still have to you'd be forced to
actually try and do something yourself
about it yeah i was thinking it reminded
me of kierkegaard actually the
the christian philosopher that he
christian philosopher that he
you know his life
well that was exactly the decision he
made exactly that was exactly the point
that he arrived at it like wait a minute
i want to be an authentic
philosopher true to the pursuit of
wisdom and at the same time i'm getting engaged
and at the same time i'm getting engaged
in planning a family in a governmental
position and work whatever was lined up
for him and then he realized well no
if i want to do this i have to say no to
this many of them wouldn't many of them would
many of them wouldn't many of them would
have uh
be quite content in perpetuity in the
idea that they are here in pursuit of
truth and clear philosophy while doing
very mundane central things
because many of them would not have been
honest as honest as he was
so then he broke off the engagement gave
everything up and then just
continue pursuing wisdom in a very
painful manner for the rest of his life
but he didn't at least he didn't
compromise and then that's quite commendable
and then that's quite commendable
yeah and somebody who does that like for
him he was really i was thinking about
he was really you know
alone you know he had nobody else who
was kind of confirming or exactly no
external structure to tell him that what
he was doing was the right thing it was
really just
and the subject also reminded me of that
again something that i'd read often in
the success but had not
paid that much attention to like when he
says
i did not go forth from this household
life for the sake of robes bowl medicine
for the sick and so on
i went forth because i was
pursued by suffering old age and death
and i thought
so i you know i used to kind of think of
that in the sense of
where people just kind of get greedy for
these things or these kind of external
whatever but
but
it can also be that you're
you know you have all of these
things that you have to get and do and
accomplish and
go to this place as a monk and
everything that it can kind of
end up obscuring your basic reason for
doing those things in the first place
and resulting complacency then
like you know you have a big community big
you know you have a big community big
place or registered everything fine
institution all settled
you know
supporters you do duties you teach
whatever else and you go through these
routines and again it's
it's all going to be rooted in just
establishing that
external sense of safety which is no
different that's the whole point of a
household life it's all you're wearing
the road the principles of a household
life still apply to you
still apply to you
so that's the
but again that's like
for everyone to see for themselves
like uh sure you could
have a relatively accurate guess
and speculation about other people's
motives if you see how they behave and
so on but overall fundamentally does
come down to every individual for for
for himself
needs to know that needs to be clear
about it
because you know it's not necessarily in
and of itself a bad thing as the buddha
said himself to my cassette i said why
do you live in the heart forest come
with me
plenty of food plenty of nice lodgings
plenty of fancy
silk robes or some whatever else
but he says no no i actually prefer this
i want to do it so externally yeah
you might think well you must not never
live in these suitable circumstances or
environment but that's that's not
guaranteed that's not a that's not a
sure symptom of an underlying problem
and sometimes equally people can go and
live in the rough forests and so on for
wrong reasons
having said that
rough forests even for wrong reasons are
less likely to give rise to unwholesome
states than the soft pleasant agreeable safe
than the soft pleasant agreeable safe
conditions would yeah
where is your sense of safety
yeah yeah or like uh yeah are you still
sort of uh taking it for granted that
you because you shouldn't have a sense
of safety upon anything that's the like
when the man when the buddha says in the
sutures in the monkeys
nothing is worth
holding on to
nothing is worth acquiring and regarding
his mind that's why i'm unsafe not
because i haven't found safety from all
the threats no it's because i'm making
myself liable to threats
so then that's the true safety when
there's nothing that you need for your
safety